<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      
      <fileDesc>
         
         <titleStmt>
            
            <title>
               
               Four Walls and a Black Veil
               
            </title>
            
         </titleStmt>
         
         <extent>8 pages</extent>
         
         <publicationStmt>
            
            <publisher>
               
               Saniya Irfan; PhD scholar (Department of Humanities and Social Sciences), IIT Delhi
               
            </publisher>
            
            <pubPlace>
               
               IIT Delhi, Hauz Khas, New Delhi
               
            </pubPlace>
            
            <date>
               
               30th December 2022</date>
            
            <availability>
               
               <p>The PDF version of this poetry collection was downloaded from Internet Archive</p>
               
            </availability>
            
         </publicationStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc>
            
            <biblFull>
               
               <titleStmt>
                  
                  <title>
                     
                     Four Walls and a Black Veil
                     
                  </title>
                  
                  <author>It's a poetry collection of Fahmida Riaz translated from Urdu to English by various translators, with a foreword by Aamer Hussein</author>
                  
               </titleStmt>
               
               <extent>8 pages</extent>
               
               <publicationStmt>
                  
                  <publisher>IIT Delhi</publisher>
                  
                  <pubPlace>Pakistan</pubPlace>
                  
                  <date>2004</date>
                  
               </publicationStmt>
               
            </biblFull>
            
         </sourceDesc>
         
      </fileDesc>
      
      <encodingDesc>
         
         <projectDesc>
            
            <p>
               This project is a sample encoding file for personal collection</p>
            
         </projectDesc>
         
         <editorialDecl><p>All spellings and punctuations are same as the original PDF</p>
            
         </editorialDecl>
         
      </encodingDesc>
      
      <!-- <revisionDesc>
        <change when="date" who="#name">The final section of the Encoding Description is the Revision Description,an optional record of changes
        made to your text. You do not need to add anything now. If you are using an XML file provided by 18thConnect.org, these
        will be a list of changes already made that you should include. Otherwise, you should consider recording both the
        changes and the individuals who performed the work to make them to prevent their labor from becoming invisible.</change>
        </revisionDesc> -->
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage facs="FR.png">
            <titlePart type="main"><hi rend="large"><hi rend="italics"><title>Four Walls and a Black
                        Veil</title><lb/></hi></hi></titlePart>
            <titlePart type="sub">Poetry from Pakistan</titlePart>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="large">Fahmida Riaz</hi></docAuthor>
            <epigraph>
               <p>Born in <placeName>Meerut</placeName>, <country>India</country>, Fahmida Riaz is
                  among the front rank of Urdu poets. From the outset she refused to be typecast as
                  a woman poet and conform to what are generally regarded as the confines of
                  'proper' literary and creative traditions of feminine poetry. In her choice of
                  themes, diction, allusion, and similes she broke out of the inhibitions imposed on
                  her gender. This was evident from the contents of her first collection of verse,
                     <hi rend="italic">Patthar Ki Zaban</hi> (published in 1967). With the
                  publication of her second collection, <hi rend="italic">Badan Dareeda</hi>, she
                  emerged as a full-fledged iconoclast. The poem, <hi rend="italic">Badan
                     Dareeda</hi>, which carried the same title as the collection, can be regarded
                  as something of a landmark, putting her in the same category as lsmat Chughtai who
                  wrote the short story <hi rend="italic">Lihaf</hi>. Fahmida Riaz used her
                  femininity as a weapon to expose the prudishness of the male-oriented traditions
                  of Urdu poetry. She has since published four more collections of her verse <hi
                     rend="italic">Dhoop</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Kya Tum Pura Chand Na
                  Dekhogay</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hamrakab and Aadmi Ki Zindigi</hi>. Fahmida Riaz
                  is also the author of several short stories and novels in Urdu: <hi rend="italic"
                     >Godavari</hi>, based on her Indian experience, and <hi rend="italic">Zinda
                     Bahar Lane</hi> based on Bangladesh.</p>
               <p>Fahmida Riaz is also an unrelenting social critic and has been active in several
                  human rights movements. She was among the writer who campaigned against General
                  Ziaul Haq's military rule and the execution of Z.A. Bhutto, and had to suffer the
                  wrath of the authorities and a period of self-exile. She has travelled widely and
                  lectured at universities and cultural forums in England and the USA. Fahmida Riaz
                  was given the Himmett-Hellman award by Human Rights Watch, <placeName>New
                     York</placeName>, in <date>1997</date></p>
            </epigraph>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Pakistan</pubPlace>
               <docDate>2004</docDate>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <div type="toc"/>
         <div type="preface"/>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poetry">
            <head>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Poetry from Pakistan</title><lb/>
                  <title>Urdu Poems with English Translations</title><lb/>
                  <hi rend="italics"><title>Four Walls and a Black Veil</title><lb/></hi>
                  <author>Fahmida Riaz</author><lb/>
               </bibl>
            </head>
            <l>Foreword</l>
            <lb/>
            <l>Fahmida Riaz: Songs of Experience</l>
            <lb/>
            <l><name ref="#AamerHussein">Aamer Hussein</name></l>
            <!--How to add link to a webpage here -->
            <lb/>
            <p>In her foreword to <hi rend="italics">Patthar ki Zaban</hi>, her first collection of
               poems, Fahmida Riaz told her readers that she never had written, and never would
               write, until a poem compelled her to give it a form; she had not attempted to write
               ghazals, as she would not make any compromises for the sake of rhythm or rhyme; and
               she foresaw herself writing for only three or four years more, as after that she
               would not have anything left to say. The year was <date>1966</date>, and Fahmida -
               who was barely twenty when she wrote these words - was writing from Government Girls
               Hostel, in <placeName>Hyderabad</placeName>, <placeName>Sindh</placeName> where she
               had, until then, spent her life.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>In her foreword to <hi rend="italics">Patthar ki Zaban</hi>, her first collection of
               poems, Fahmida Riaz told her readers that she never had written, and never would
               write, until a poem compelled her to give it a form; she had not attempted to write
               ghazals, as she would not make any compromises for the sake of rhythm or rhyme; and
               she foresaw herself writing for only three or four years more, as after that she
               would not have anything left to say. The year was <date>1966</date>, and Fahmida -
               who was barely twenty when she wrote these words - was writing from Government Girls
               Hostel, in <placeName>Hyderabad</placeName>, <placeName>Sindh</placeName> where she
               had, until then, spent her life two full-length works in English: a controversial
               critical study of Pakistani literature, and an as yet unpublished novel).</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>But we first return to the years in between and to Fahmida's first collection of
               poems. The beauty of these early poems - including the title poem and <hi
                  rend="italics">'The Soft Fragrance of My Jasmine'</hi> - is unquestionable. Not
               only are their subject matter and their refusal to conform to the conventions of Urdu
               verse exceptional, their imagery is graceful, their syntax pure, their effect
               haunting and musical. But perhaps the reader is still unprepared for the power of <hi
                  rend="italics">'Badan Darida'</hi>, the volume that followed. We do have, in
               fiction, the example of Ismat Chughtai who in <hi rend="italics">Terhi Lakeer</hi>
               <date>(1944)</date> foregrounded a woman's experience with often shocking frankness;
               but to accomplish it in verse, to tum raw experience into exquisite poems without
               compromising either experience or poetry, is a measure of Fahmida' s groundbreaking
               achievement not just in Urdu poetry but in the poetry of the world.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>By then she had married and moved for some years to <placeName>London</placeName>,
               where one imagines she must have encountered the literature and art of other
               languages and cultures, and probably been exposed to the emerging currents of
               feminist thought. In <placeName>London</placeName> she had also become a mother. She
               then returned in the <date>1970s</date> to a very different life in
                  <placeName>Pakistan</placeName> and settled in <placeName>Karachi</placeName>,
               where before she remarried she was a divorced working mother. Desire, motherhood,
               married love, menstruation, taboos, social constraints, cultural restrictions - all
               find their way into Fahmida's poems of those years, in unexpected and stirring
               patterns of intertwined boldness and subtlety.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Poems such as <hi rend="italics">'The Laughter of a Woman'</hi> and <hi
                  rend="italics">'She is a Woman</hi> Impure' celebrate femininity in ways that
               French feminist theorists such as Julia Kristeva, Helene Cixous and Luce Irigaray
               were to do. Just as Chughtai prefigured by several years Simone de Beauvoir's
               theoretical configurations in The Second Sex, so, too, Fahmida wrote fearlessly about
               blood, milk and the waters of birth before her western contemporaries began to
               formulate their theories of women's writing as grounded in bodily experience, and
               most certaini: oefore she could have been exposed to their writings.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>What comes across most vividly, though, is the visionary grace and the indomitable
               spirit of a poet who is not only arguably Pakistan's leading woman writer, but also
               one of the half-dozen most distinguished Urdu writers of the past three decades. To
               attempt to do full justice to her multiple talents in the few pages of this foreword
               is as impossible a task as it would be to do her work full justice in translation: we
               can only content ourselves with projected shadows of the real thing. There is a
               remarkable continuity, though, between Fahmida's early foreword and the verses of one
               of her more recent poems:</p>
            <lb/>
            <l>She always said what she had to say,</l>
            <lb/>
            <l>And for her life she had no regrets.</l>
            <lb/>
            <l><name type="place">London</name>, <date>Janurary 2004></date></l>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <l><hi rend="caps">ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</hi></l>
            <lb/>
            <p>I am deeply indebted to Salman Tarik Kureshi who read my poems and reviewed the
               English translations. His advice and suggestions have enormously improved the quality
               of these renditions.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <l><hi rend="caps">TRANSLATORS</hi></l>

            <p><hi rend="bold">PATRICIA L. SHARPE</hi> holds a doctorate in American Literature. She
               has studied Hindi at <name type="university">Delhi University</name> and has
               published translations of several Hindi short stories. A collection of her poetry
               titled The Deadmen and Other Poems was published by Writers' Workshop in <name
                  type="place">Kolkata</name> in <date>2001</date>. Several other volumes are in
               preparation. As an American foreign service officer and journalist, Patricia has
               worked in many areas of the world, but <name type="place">South Asia</name> is the
               second home of her heart, where as a senior Fulbright scholar she taught American
               Literature at <name type="university">Punjab University</name> in <name type="place"
                  >Lahore.</name></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">RUKHSANA AHMAD</hi> is an author and playwright and taught English
               Literature at the <name type="university">University of Karachi</name> before moving
               to <name type="place">England</name> where she now lives and works.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">BAIDAR BAKHT</hi> has translated into English the work of several
               Urdu poets. He lives in <name type="place">Toronto, Canada.</name></p>
            <pb n="3"/>

            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <bibl><title><hi rend="bold">TONGUE OF STONE</hi></title>
                     <author>Fahmida Riaz</author>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <lg type="stanza">

                  <l rend="indent 6"><hi rend="bold">Translated by Patricia L. Sharpe</hi></l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">This is the lonely mountain</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">where we met, these the heights</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">where we melted into one</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">This is the wind-swept boulder of my pledge,</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">stark and desolate.</l>
                  <lb/>
                  <l rend="indent 6">For an age now</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">I have clung to this stone,</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">my dress rent and flapping in the wild wind, your breath
                     tangled in my torn shawl.</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">Balancing, trembling, I embrace this keen-edged rock</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">It has pierced my breast so deep, my lifeblood crimsons</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">the rock around me.</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">This long age I have clung here. I send a soaring bird</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">with my message for you</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">Come and look.</l>
                  <l rend="indent 6">You will be delighted. The cinders and gravel have turned to
                     rubies, they gleam! A rose blossoms from the rock.</l>
               </lg>
               <fw type="sig"><pb n="4"/></fw>
            </div>

            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <bibl>
                     <title>SURAH-E-YASEEN<note>1. Surah-e-Yaseen: It is a chapter of the Quran that is
                        recited to soothe the agony of death. This surah is read out to the dying. The
                        title of this poem hints at entering into the unknown.</note></title>
                     <author>Fahmida Riaz</author>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <lg type="stanza">

                  <l><hi rend="bold">Translated by Rukhsana Ahmad</hi></l>
                  <lb/>
                  <l>Late at night, this eerie silence!</l>
                  <l>In this dimly dark pathway,</l>
                  <l>With hurriedly advancing footsteps, I'm a lone woman.</l>
                  <l> For a long time now I have been hearing the sound of footsteps following me.
                     Home!</l>
                  <l>My home!</l>
                  <l>How do I get to my home?</l>
                  <l>With parched throat and a sinking heart I think Perhaps I have forgotten my
                     way,</l>
                  <l>this way is not my Way,</l>
                  <l>all the alleyways are marked here</l>
                  <l>this alley has no name</l>
                  <l>and for miles and miles, holding their breath</l>
                  <l>all these houses, are unfamiliar</l>
                  <l>There! Even the fragmented yellow moon</l>
                  <l>has drowned in the dark leaves</l>
                  <l>Now there is nothing</l>
                  <l>Except in my mouth,</l>
                  <l>heavy with fear and paralysed, my tongue.</l>
                  <l>Or rising upwards, through the soles of my
                        feet, suffusing in each and every pore of my body, certain
                     dampness.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="5"/>
            </div>

            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <bibl>
                     <title>AQLEEMA<note>
Aqleema: In the Islamic legend, Aqleema was the sister of Abel and Cain who both wanted to marry her. God decided to resolve the dispute by asking them to bring their offerings. He accepted Abel's offering, a fat lamb and gave Aqleema's hand to him. Aqleema's preference never figured in His decision.
                     </note></title>
                     <author>Fahmida Riaz</author>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <lg type="stanza">

                  <l><hi rend="bold">Translated by Rukhsana Ahmad</hi></l>
                  <lb/>
                  <l>Aqleema</l>
                  <l>Who is the sister of Cain and Abel Born of the same mother</l>
                  <l>But she is different.</l>
                  <l>Different between her thighs</l>
                  <l>And in the bulge of her breasts Different in her gut</l>
                  <l>And inside her womb</l>
                  <l>Why is the fate of all of these</l>
                  <l>The sacrifice of a fatted Iamb?</l>
                  <l>Imprisoned by her own body Burning in the scalding sun She stands on a
                     hilltop</l>
                  <l>Like a mark etched on stone Look at this mark carefully Above the long thighs
                     Above the high breasts Above the tangled womb Aqleema has a head too</l>
                  <l>Let God speak to Aqleema sometime And ask her something.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="6"/>
            </div>

            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <bibl>
                     <title>SEARCH WARRANT<note>The Interrogator and Search Warrant: Both the poems were written during Zia's
                        regime when I was frequently subjected to police interrogation and house
                        search.</note></title>
                     <author>Fahmida Riaz</author>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l><hi rend="bold">Translated by Rukhsana Ahmad</hi></l>
                  <lb/>
                  <l>The interrogator:</l>
                  <l>'Look here Bibi, here is the Search Warrant;</l>
                  <l>The contingents are with me, but I left them round the comer I thought, I can
                     manage on my own.</l>
                  <l>We are looking for a piece of writing.</l>
                  <l>What's the point in making a scene?</l>
                  <l>Fetch it yourself.</l>
                  <l>Or, else, where it lies, hidden in the house,</l>
                  <l>Show us, without a fuss'</l>
                  <l>Never have I seen my house in this light</l>
                  <l>I can hear a heartbeat throb in its very walls</l>
                  <l>Blood drips from the veins of stones and steel</l>
                  <l>Warm breaths, wakeful eyes, parted lips surround me</l>
                  <l>Repeat their whisper to me once again</l>
                  <l>Of the promised eternal bond with my country My four walls, dear land, nestle
                     in your arms The few moments of refuge I had, I owe you. Countless cellars
                     arise before my eyes Countless possibilities open their doors for me Beneath my
                     feet opens the tunnel of my hopes ! All seven colours of life glowing on its
                     walls.</l>
                  <l>New words will be inscribed now on the walls of the city 0 passing moment</l>
                  <l>I swear by your desecrated honour Red is the dust around my house Beyond</l>
                  <l>this window blooms a red flower </l>
                  <l>All these tribulations over a book Hidden in my</l>
                  <l>past? </l>
                  <l>Look beyond the curtains instead At my dreams of the future </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="7"/>
            </div>

            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <bibl>
                     <title>THE INTERROGATER</title>
                     <author>Fahmida Riaz</author>
                  </bibl>
               </head>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l><hi rend="bold">Translated by Rukhsana Ahmad</hi></l>
                  <lb/>
                  <l>The Interrogator is waiting What should be our statement?</l>
                  <l>How life has suffered</l>
                  <l>It is hard to reveal</l>
                  <l>What the heart has endured Impossible to recount.</l>
                  <l>Here is my statement then:</l>
                  <l>Take note then, this is all true.</l>
                  <l>All the allegations are true</l>
                  <l>My crime is proven</l>
                  <l>What I did though, was too little</l>
                  <l>That is my only regret</l>
                  <l>I hope I may have another chance</l>
                  <l>I owed more than I have paid as yet</l>
                  <l>To all that, add this too</l>
                  <l>So long as I breathe</l>
                  <l>I shall do it again</l>
                  <l>If possible I shall do it better</l>
                  <l>We shall write that word again</l>
                  <l>To make every dictator equipped with his armoury Tremble upon reading that
                     word</l>
                  <l>We shall play that tune again</l>
                  <l>To make every victim of oppression,</l>
                  <l>With bands of folded hands.</l>
                  <l>Dance to its rhythm.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="8"/>
            </div>
            <div type="notes">
               <l><hi rend="bold">Notes</hi></l>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
